

JEREMY LIGHTSMITH

For over 20 years, I've helped software teams deliver more value and find happiness at work.

I've done this by writing good code, steering technical direction, mediating conflict, and helping teams design their process. I'm just as much at home writing code with developers as I am in the boardroom, and just as happy to follow as to lead.

I'm looking for a developer position where my leadership and process background can make a big impact.

EXPERTISE

Lean + Kanban
Agile / Scrum
eXtreme Programming
Design Thinking
Facilitation
Mediation
Human Systems
Dynamics
Liberating Structures
Unit Testing
Story Mapping
Enterprise Architecture

Ruby + Rails
React + Redux
JavaScript
Clojure
C#
Swift

Java

EDUCATION

University of Southern California BS in Computer Science EXPERIENCE -

Transparent Classroom

2012 - present

FOUNDER / CEO / DEVELOPER (Ruby / JS)

Transparent Classroom is the industry leader for Montessori school record keeping and lesson planning. I grew it from a project I hacked on nights and weekends to a team of 9 that serves 100K+ children in 1,300 Montessori schools across 65 countries with 1M+ revenue.

Outpace Systems, Inc

2014 - 2016

TEAM LEAD / DEVELOPER (Clojure)

I led the team working on a rules engine, the heart of this 60-person startup. In addition to writing code and leading my team, I set up effective remote-first meeting practices, facilitated our bi-annual in person conference, and introduced processes and tools for managing work company-wide.

Nordstrom Innovation Lab

2011 - 2013

COACH / DEVELOPER (Ruby / JS)

As coach, I led the team in adapting processes like Lean Startup, Liberating Structures, and Design Thinking into our own innovation process. As developer, I built prototypes and early stage products at breakneck speed to validate our hypotheses.

Lightsmith Consulting LLC

2009 - 2013

I worked with and coached teams that want to be more lean and agile. Engagements ranged from afternoon trainings to multi-year embedded coaching and delivery.

AGILE COACH (C#), Client: Vertafore, Insurance Company

Helped their 40-developer team through their third year of agile adoption. I introduced dev practices, coached scrum masters, and led workshops.

INSTRUCTOR (Ruby), Client: University of Washington

Designed and taught a 10-week Ruby on Rails course.

SENIOR DEVELOPER (C#), Client: SerialsSolutions

Worked on Rails frontend for a next generation library search service.

Pivotal Labs 2007 - 2009

Pivotal provides on-demand project teams for well-funded startups. As an "anchor," I led teams and managed scope / customers. I also introduced Pivotal to starting projects with 2 week inceptions - which became part of the "Pivotal Way."

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / LEAD (Ruby), Client: Major Construction Company

Led punchlist product from inception to launch. Requirements included handling millions of records, concurrent users, and offline access. We delivered on time and budget.

CLIENT PRINCIPAL / LEAD (Ruby), Client: Construction Services Company

My 6-person team did a rewrite of their flagship product from Java to Rails in 6 months.

SENIOR DEVELOPER (Ruby), Product: Pivotal Tracker

As a senior developer, I worked on a UI overhaul of Pivotal Tracker as we pushed it toward full public release.

jeremy.lightsmith@gmail.com jeremylightsmith.com LinkedIn Seattle, WA (312) 953-1193

ThoughtWorks Inc.

2000 - 2007

I served as a coach, developer, and facilitator to many projects during my tenure. I learned a ton and even got to pair with people like Ward Cunningham, Martin Fowler, Robert Martin, and Brian Marick.

LEAD FACILITATOR / TRAINER, QuickStart Engagements

Started several small to multi-million projects with inceptions and trained other facilitators to give them.

DEV LEAD / PRODUCT OWNER (Ruby), Product: CruiseControl.rb

Led team to deliver 1.0 Ruby version of Cruise Control which became the gold standard for Ruby continuous integration.

PRODUCT CONSULTANT (C#), Client: Language Workbench Product Company

Drove requirements and served as industry expert for next generation Domain Specific Language IDE.

AGILE COACH / SENIOR ARCHITECT (C#), Client: Major Financial Company
Helped 30-person team adopt agile across 3 sites and pioneered .NET architecture in the early days.

SENIOR DEVELOPER / TEAM LEAD (Java), *Client: Major Petroleum Company*Helped set methodology and architecture on 100+ person project, and migrated data from 100+ legacy tables.

AGILE COACH / DEV LEAD (Java), *Client: Container Shipping Web Service* Introduced XP to the client and pioneered n-stage XSLT for generating HTML.

IBM Corp. 1999 - 2000

DEVELOPER / TEAM LEAD (C++)

Led the Windows GUI team on a large-scale cross-platform C++/Java environment.

OTHER EXPERIENCE -

Retreat of TBD 2018 - present

CO-FOUNDER / OPEN SPACE FACILITATOR

Human Systems Dynamics Institute 2018 - 2020

BOARD MEMBER

Agile Open Northwest 2015 - 2020

BOARD MEMBER / OPEN SPACE FACILITATOR

Chautaugua Retreat 2012 - 2017

CO-FOUNDER / OPEN SPACE FACILITATOR

Lighthouse Montessori School 2008 - present

CO-FOUNDER / BOARD CHAIR

Burn Blue 2007 - 2013

CO-FOUNDER / DIRECTOR

References available upon request